<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2002-2004 The Apache Software Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Simplified DocBook XML V1.0//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/simple/1.0/sdocbook.dtd">
<article id="bk_GettStartedGuide">
  <title>ZooKeeper Getting Started Guide</title>

  <articleinfo>
    <legalnotice>
      <para>Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You may
      obtain a copy of the License at <ulink
      url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
      software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or
      implied. See the License for the specific language governing permissions
      and limitations under the License.</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <abstract>
      <para>This guide contains detailed information about creating
      distributed applications that use ZooKeeper. It discusses the basic
      operations Zookeeper supports, and how these can be used to build
      higher-level abstractions. It contains solutions to common tasks, a
      troubleshooting guide, and links to other information.</para>
    </abstract>
  </articleinfo>

  <section id="ch_GettingStarted">
    <title>Getting Started: Coordinating Distributed Applications with
      ZooKeeper</title>

    <para>This document contains information to get you started quickly with
    Zookeeper. It is aimed primarily at developers hoping to try it out, and
    contains simple installation instructions for a single ZooKeeper server, a
    few commands to verify that it is running, and a simple programming
    example. Finally, as a convenience, there are a few sections regarding
    more complicated installations, for example running replicated
    deployments, and optimizing the transaction log. However for the complete
    instructions for commercial deployments, please refer to the <ulink
    url="zookeeperAdmin.html">Zookeeper
    Administrator's Guide</ulink>.</para>

    <section id="sc_InstallingSingleMode">
      <title>Installing and Running ZooKeeper in Single Server Mode</title>

      <para>Setting up a ZooKeeper server in standalone mode is
      straightforward. The server is contained in a single JAR file, so
      installation consists of copying a JAR file and creating a
      configuration.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Zookeeper requires Java 1.5 or more recent.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Once you have downloaded the ZooKeeper source, cd to the root of
      your ZooKeeper source, and run "ant jar". For example:<computeroutput>$ cd ~/dev/zookeeper

$ ~/dev/zookeeper/: ant jar</computeroutput></para>

      <para>This should generate a JAR file called zookeeper.jar. To start
      Zookeeper, compile and run zookeeper.jar. <emphasis>[tbd, some more
      instruction here. Perhaps a command line? Are these two steps or
      one?]</emphasis></para>

      <para>To start ZooKeeper you need a configuration file. Here is a sample
      file:</para>

      <programlisting>tickTime=2000
dataDir=/var/zookeeper/ 
clientPort=2181
</programlisting>

      <para>This file can be called anything, but for the sake of this
      discussion, call it <emphasis role="bold">zoo.cfg</emphasis>. Here are
      the meanings for each of the fields:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">tickTime</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>the basic time unit in milliseconds used by ZooKeeper. It is
            used to do heartbeats and the minimum session timeout will be
            twice the tickTime.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">dataDir</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>the location to store the in-memory database snapshots and,
            unless specified otherwise, the transaction log of updates to the
            database.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">clientPort</emphasis></term>

          <listitem>
            <para>the port to listen for client connections</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>Now that you created the configuration file, you can start
      ZooKeeper:</para>

      <para><computeroutput>java -cp zookeeper-dev.jar:java/lib/log4j-1.2.15.jar:conf org.apache.zookeeper.server.quorum.QuorumPeerMain zoo.cfg</computeroutput></para>

      <para>ZooKeeper logs messages using log4j -- more detail available in
      the <ulink url="zookeeperProgrammers.html#Logging">Logging</ulink>
      section of the Programmer's Guide.<emphasis>[tbd:
      real reference needed]</emphasis> You will see log messages coming to the
      console and/or a log file depending on the log4j configuration.</para>

      <para>The steps outlined here run ZooKeeper in standalone mode. There is
      no replication, so if Zookeeper process fails, the service will go down.
      This is fine for most development situations, but to run Zookeeper in
      replicated mode, please see <ulink
      url="#sc_RunningReplicatedZooKeeper">Running Replicated
      Zookeeper</ulink>.</para>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section id="sc_ConnectingToZooKeeper">
      <title>Connecting to ZooKeeper</title>

      <para>Once ZooKeeper is running, you have several option for connection
      to it:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">Java</emphasis>: Use java -cp
          zookeeper.jar:java/lib/log4j-1.2.15.jar:conf
          org.apache.zookeeper.ZooKeeperMain 127.0.0.1:2181</para>

          <para>This lets you perform simple, file-like operations.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis role="bold">C</emphasis>: compile cli_mt
          (multi-threaded) or cli_st (single-threaded) by running
          <command>_make cli_mt_</command> or <command>_make cli_st_</command>
          in the c subdirectory in the ZooKeeper sources.</para>

          <para>You can run the program using <emphasis>LD_LIBRARY_PATH=.
          cli_mt 127.0.0.1:2181</emphasis> or <emphasis>LD_LIBRARY_PATH=.
          cli_st 127.0.0.1:2181</emphasis>. This will give you a simple shell
          to execute file system like operations on ZooKeeper.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="sc_ProgrammingToZooKeeper">
      <title>Programming to ZooKeeper</title>

      <para>ZooKeeper has a Java bindings and C bindings. They are
      functionally equivalent. The C bindings exist in two variants: single
      threaded and multi-threaded. These differ only in how the messaging loop
      is done. For more information, see the <ulink
      url="zookeeperProgrammers.html#ch_programStructureWithExample.html">Programming
      Examples in the Zookeeper Programmer's Guide</ulink> for
      sample code using of the different APIs.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="sc_RunningReplicatedZooKeeper">
      <title>Running Replicated ZooKeeper</title>

      <para>Running ZooKeeper in standalone mode is convenient for evaluation,
      some development, and testing. But in production, you should run
      ZooKeeper in replicated mode. A replicated group of servers in the same
      application is called a <emphasis>quorum</emphasis>, and in replicated
      mode, all servers in the quorum have copies of the same configuration
      file. The file is similar to the one used in standalone mode, but with a
      few differences. Here is an example:</para>

      <para><computeroutput>tickTime=2000 
dataDir=/var/zookeeper/ 
clientPort=2181 
initLimit=5 
syncLimit=2 
server.1=zoo1:2888 server.2=zoo2:2888 
server.3=zoo3:2888 </computeroutput></para>

      <para>The new entry, <emphasis role="bold">initLimit</emphasis> is
      timeouts ZooKeeper uses to limit the length of time the Zookeeper
      servers in quorum have to connect to a leader. The entry <emphasis
      role="bold">syncLimit</emphasis> limits how far out of date a server can
      be from a leader.</para>

      <para>With both of these timeouts, you specify the unit of time using
      <emphasis role="bold">tickTime</emphasis>. In this example, the timeout
      for initLimit is 5 ticks at 2000 milleseconds a tick, or 10
      seconds.</para>

      <para>The entries of the form <emphasis>server.X</emphasis> list the
      servers that make up the ZooKeeper service. When the server starts up,
      it knows which server it is by looking for the file *myid* in the data
      directory. That file has the contains the server number, in
      ASCII.</para>

      <para>Finally, note the "2888" port numbers after each server name.
      These are the "electionPort" numbers of the servers (as opposed to
      clientPorts), that is ports for <emphasis>[tbd]</emphasis>.</para>

      <note>
        <para>If you want to test multiple servers on a single machine, define
        the electionPort for each server in that server's config file, using
        the line <command>electionPort=xxxx</command> as means of avoiding
        clashes.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Other Optimizations</title>

      <para>There are a couple of other configuration parameters that can
      greatly increase performance:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To get low latencies on updates it is important to have a
          dedicated transaction log directory. By default transaction logs are
          put in the same directory as the data snapshots and *myid* file. The
          dataLogDir parameters indicates a different directory to use for the
          transaction logs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>[tbd: what is the other config param?]</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</article>
